<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rdf:RDF xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" xmlns:rdakit="http://metadataregistry.org/uri/profile/rdakit/" xmlns:owl="http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:reg="http://metadataregistry.org/uri/profile/regap/" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:vann="http://purl.org/vocab/vann/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">

<!-- Scheme: RDA Recording Methods -->
    <skos:ConceptScheme rdf:about="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDARecordingMethods">
        <dc:title xml:lang="en">RDA Recording Methods</dc:title>
    <dc:description xml:lang="en">Concepts for a method used to record a value of an RDA element.</dc:description>
        <vann:preferredNamespacePrefix>rdapath</vann:preferredNamespacePrefix>
        
        
        
        <dc:rights xml:lang="en">Copyright © 2020 American Library Association, Canadian Federation of Library Associations, and CILIP: Chartered Institute of Library and Information Professionals</dc:rights>
        <cc:licence rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en_US"/>
        <dc:creator>RDA Steering Committee</dc:creator>
        <dc:contributor>RSC Technical Working Group</dc:contributor>
        <dc:publisher>ALA Digital Reference</dc:publisher>
        <dc:type rdf:resource="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDALinkedDataWork/1002"/>
    
        <owl:versionInfo>v4.0.12</owl:versionInfo>
        <dc:modified rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#date">2021-07-08</dc:modified>
        <dc:issued rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#date">2017-10-16</dc:issued>
    </skos:ConceptScheme>

<!-- Concept: identifier  -->
    <skos:Concept rdf:about="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDARecordingMethods/1003" xml:lang="en">
      <skos:inScheme rdf:resource="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDARecordingMethods"/>
      <reg:status rdf:resource="http://metadataregistry.org/uri/RegStatus/1001"/>
      
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">identifier</skos:prefLabel>
      <skos:notation>1003</skos:notation>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="en">identifier</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="en">A recording method that is a machine-readable string that is assigned to an entity in order to differentiate the entity from other entities within a local domain, or a notation for a term from a controlled vocabulary that is assigned to an aspect of the entity.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="en">Includes an identifier or notation taken from a vocabulary encoding scheme.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">identifiant</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="fr">identifiant</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="fr">Méthode d’enregistrement qui consiste soit en une chaîne lisible par machine et assignée à une entité dans le but de différencier l’entité d’autres entités au sein d’un domaine local, soit en une notation qui provient d’un vocabulaire contrôlé et est assignée à un aspect de l’entité.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="fr">Comprend un identifiant ou une notation provenant d’un schéma d’encodage de vocabulaire.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">identifikator</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="da">identifikator</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="da">Streng der er tildelt en entitet for at differentiere entiteten fra andre entiteter inden for et lokalt domæne, eller en notation fra et kontrolleret vokabular, der er tildelt et aspekt af entiteten.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="da">Omfatter en identifikator eller notation taget fra et vokabularkodningsskema.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">tunniste</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="fi">tunniste</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="fi">Merkitsemistapa, jossa koneluettava merkkijono on liitetty entiteettiin sen erottamiseksi muista paikallisen nimialueen entiteeteistä tai jossa kontrolloidun sanaston notaatio on liitetty entiteetin ominaisuuteen.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="fi">Merkitsemistapa sisältää tunnisteen tai sanaston merkintäjärjestelmän notaation.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">identificador</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="ca">identificador</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="ca">Cadena que és assignada a una entitat per diferenciar l'entitat d'altres entitats dins un domini local, o una notació obtinguda d'un vocabulari controlat que és assignada a un aspecte de l'entitat.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="ca">Inclou un identificador o una notació obtinguts d'un esquema de codificació d'un vocabulari.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">αναγνωριστικό</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="el">αναγνωριστικό</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="el">Μια μέθοδος καταγραφής που είναι ένας μηχαναγνώσιμος αλφαριθμητικός χαρακτήρας, ο οποίος ανατίθεται σε μια οντότητα προκειμένου να διαφοροποιήσει μια οντότητα από άλλες οντότητες εντός ενός τοπικού τομέα, ή μια σημειογραφία για έναν όρο από ένα ελεγχόμενο λεξιλόγιο ο οποίος ανατίθεται σε μια πτυχή της οντότητας. </rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="el">Περιλαμβάνει ένα αναγνωριστικό ή μια σημειογραφία που αντλείται από ένα σχήμα κωδικοποίησης [του] λεξιλογίου. </skos:scopeNote>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">identifikator</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="no">identifikator</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="no">En tekststreng som er knyttet til en entitet for å skille entiteten fra andre entiteter i et lokalt domene, eller en notasjon fra et kontrollert vokabular som er knyttet til et aspekt ved entiteten.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="no">Inkluderer en identifikator eller notasjon hentet fra et kodeskjema for vokabular.</skos:scopeNote>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">Identifikator</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="de">Identifikator</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="de">Eine Erfassungsmethode entweder in Form einer maschinenlesbaren Zeichenkette, die einer Entität zugewiesen wird, um sie von anderen Entitäten innerhalb der lokalen Domain zu unterscheiden, oder in Form einer Notation (als System von Zeichen oder Symbolen einer Metasprache) zu einer Bezeichnung aus einem kontrollierten Vokabular, die einer Eigenschaft einer Entität zugewiesen wird.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="de">Eine Erfassungsmethode entweder in Form einer maschinenlesbaren Zeichenkette, die einer Entität zugewiesen wird, um sie von anderen Entitäten innerhalb der lokalen Domain zu unterscheiden, oder in Form einer Notation (als System von Zeichen oder Symbolen einer Metasprache) zu einer Bezeichnung aus einem kontrollierten Vokabular, die einer Eigenschaft einer Entität zugewiesen wird.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="de">Darunter fallen auch Identifikatoren oder Notationen (von Systemstellen), die einem Vocabulary Encoding Scheme entnommen sind.</skos:scopeNote>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="fr">Méthode d’enregistrement qui consiste soit en une chaîne lisible par machine et assignée à une entité dans le but de différencier l’entité d’autres entités au sein d’un domaine local, soit en une notation qui provient d’un vocabulaire contrôlé et est assignée à un aspect de l’entité.</skos:definition>
        <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">azonosító</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="hu">azonosító</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="hu">A rögzítés egy módja, ami egy olyan géppel olvasható karakterlánc, amelyet egy entitáshoz rendeltek hozzá, hogy az entitást elkülönítsék az adott helyi hálózati tartományon belül található további entitásoktól, vagy egy kontrollált szótárból származó jelölés, amelyet egy entitás egy aspektusához rendeltek hozzá.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="hu">A rögzítés egy módja, ami egy olyan géppel olvasható karakterlánc, amelyet egy entitáshoz rendeltek hozzá, hogy az entitást elkülönítsék az adott helyi hálózati tartományon belül található további entitásoktól, vagy egy kontrollált szótárból származó jelölés, amelyet egy entitás egy aspektusához rendeltek hozzá.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="hu">Idetartoznak az egy szótár kódolási sémájából származó azonosítók és jelölések.</skos:scopeNote>
        <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">identificatore</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="it">identificatore</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="it">Metodo di registrazione che usa una stringa assegnata a un'entità, in una forma leggibile da una macchina, o una notazione da un vocabolario controllato che è assegnata a un aspetto dell'entità, al fine di differenziare l'entità da altre entità in un dominio locale.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="it">Stringa assegnata a un'entità al fine di differenziare l'entità da altre entità in un dominio locale o una notazione da un vocabolario controllato che è assegnata a un aspetto dell'entità.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="it">Include un identificatore o una notazione tratti da un schema di codifica di un vocabolario.</skos:scopeNote>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="et">identifikaator</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="et">identifikaator</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="et">Märkimisviis on masinloetav string, mis on määratud olemile selle eristamiseks piiritletud valdkonna teistest olemitest, või kontrollitava sõnastiku terminit tähistav notatsioon, mis on määratud olemi mingile aspektile.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="et">Märkimisviis on masinloetav string, mis on määratud olemile selle eristamiseks piiritletud valdkonna teistest olemitest, või kontrollitava sõnastiku terminit tähistav notatsioon, mis on määratud olemi mingile aspektile.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="et">Hõlmab leksikaalsest märkimissüsteemist võetud identifikaatorit ja notatsiooni.</skos:scopeNote>
    </skos:Concept>
<!-- Concept: IRI  -->
    <skos:Concept rdf:about="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDARecordingMethods/1004" xml:lang="en">
      <skos:inScheme rdf:resource="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDARecordingMethods"/>
      <reg:status rdf:resource="http://metadataregistry.org/uri/RegStatus/1001"/>
      
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
      <skos:notation>1004</skos:notation>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="en">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="en">A recording method that is a machine-readable string that is assigned to an entity in order to differentiate the entity from other entities, or to an aspect of an entity, within the global domain of the semantic web and open linked data.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="fr">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="fr">Méthode d’enregistrement qui consiste en une chaîne lisible par machine et assignée à une entité dans le but de différencier l’entité d’autres entités, ou à un aspect d’une entité, au sein du domaine mondial du Web sémantique et des données ouvertes liées.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="da">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="da">Streng, der er tildelt en entitet for at differentiere entiteten fra andre entiteter, eller til et aspekt af en entitet, inden for det globale domæne af den semantiske web og åbne linkede data.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="fi">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="fi">Merkitsemistapa, jossa semanttisen webin ja avoimen linkitetyn datan kansainväliseen nimialueeseen sisältyvä koneluettava merkkijono on liitetty entiteettiin tai entiteetin ominaisuuteen niiden erottamiseksi muista entiteeteistä ja niiden ominaisuuksista.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="ca">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="ca">Cadena que s'assigna a una entitat per diferenciar l'entitat d'altres entitats, o assignada a un aspecte d'una entitat, dins el domini global de la web semàntica i de les dades enllaçades obertes.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="el">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="el">Μια μέθοδος καταγραφής που είναι ένας μηχαναγνώσιμος αλφαριθμητικός χαρακτήρας, ο οποίος ανατίθεται σε μια οντότητα προκειμένου να τη διαφοροποιήσει από άλλες οντότητες ή σε μια πτυχή μιας οντότητας εντός του παγκόσμιου τομέα του σημασιολογικού ιστού και των ανοικτών συνδεδεμένων δεδομένων. </rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="no">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="no">En tekststreng som er knyttet til en entitet for å skille entiteten eller aspekter ved entiteten fra andre entiteter i det globale domenet av den semantiske veven og som åpne, lenkede data. </rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:altLabel xml:lang="en">Internationalized Resource Identifier</skos:altLabel>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">International Resource Identifier (IRI)</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="de">International Resource Identifier (IRI)</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="de">Eine Erfassungsmethode innerhalb der globalen Domain des Semantic Web und Open Linked Data in Form einer maschinenlesbaren Zeichenkette, die einer Entität oder einer Eigenschaft einer Entität zugewiesen wird, um sie von anderen Entitäten zu unterscheiden.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="de">Eine Erfassungsmethode innerhalb der globalen Domain des Semantic Web und Open Linked Data in Form einer maschinenlesbaren Zeichenkette, die einer Entität oder einer Eigenschaft einer Entität zugewiesen wird, um sie von anderen Entitäten zu unterscheiden.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="fr">Méthode d’enregistrement qui consiste en une chaîne lisible par machine et assignée à une entité dans le but de différencier l’entité d’autres entités, ou à un aspect d’une entité, au sein du domaine mondial du Web sémantique et des données ouvertes liées.</skos:definition>
        <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="hu">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="hu">A rögzítés egy módja, ami egy olyan géppel olvasható karakterlánc, amelyet egy entitáshoz rendeltek hozzá, hogy az entitást elkülönítsék a további entitásoktól a szemantikus web és a nyílt kapcsolt adatok globális hálózati tartományán belül, vagy amelyet egy entitás egy aspektusához rendeltek hozzá hasonló célból.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="hu">A rögzítés egy módja, ami egy olyan géppel olvasható karakterlánc, amelyet egy entitáshoz rendeltek hozzá, hogy az entitást elkülönítsék a további entitásoktól a szemantikus web és a nyílt kapcsolt adatok globális hálózati tartományán belül, vagy amelyet egy entitás egy aspektusához rendeltek hozzá hasonló célból.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="it">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="it">Metodo di registrazione che usa una stringa assegnata a un'entità, o a un aspetto di un'entità, in una forma leggibile da una macchina, al fine di differenziare l'entità da altre entità nel dominio globale del web semantico e degli open linked data.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="it">Stringa assegnata a un'entità al fine di differenziare l'entità da altre entità o a un aspetto di un'entità nel dominio globlae del web semantico e degli open linked data.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="et">IRI</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="et">IRI</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="et">Märkimisviis on masinloetav string, mis on semantilise veebi ja lingitud avaandmete üleilmses keskkonnas määratud olemile selle eristamiseks teistest olemitest või olemi mingile aspektile.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="et">Märkimisviis on masinloetav string, mis on semantilise veebi ja lingitud avaandmete üleilmses keskkonnas määratud olemile selle eristamiseks teistest olemitest või olemi mingile aspektile.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
    </skos:Concept>
<!-- Concept: structured description  -->
    <skos:Concept rdf:about="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDARecordingMethods/1002" xml:lang="en">
      <skos:inScheme rdf:resource="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDARecordingMethods"/>
      <reg:status rdf:resource="http://metadataregistry.org/uri/RegStatus/1001"/>
      
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">structured description</skos:prefLabel>
      <skos:notation>1002</skos:notation>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="en">structured description</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="en">A recording method that is a human-readable string that is a full or partial description of an entity that is based on a string encoding scheme, or is a controlled term that describes an aspect of an entity.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="en">Includes an access point or a controlled term taken from a vocabulary encoding scheme.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">description structurée</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="fr">description structurée</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="fr">Méthode d’enregistrement qui consiste soit en une chaîne lisible par l’humain et constituée d’une description complète ou partielle d’une entité basée sur un schéma d’encodage de chaînes, soit en un terme contrôlé décrivant un aspect d’une entité.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="fr">Comprend un point d’accès ou un terme contrôlé provenant d’un schéma d’encodage de vocabulaire.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">struktureret beskrivelse</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="da">struktureret beskrivelse</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="da">Streng, der er en hel eller delvis beskrivelse af en entitet baseret på en syntaks- eller strengkodningsskema eller en kontrolleret term der beskriver et aspekt af en entitet.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="da">Omfatter en søgeindgang eller en kontrolleret term der er tagen fra et vokabularkodningsskema.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">rakenteistettu kuvailu</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="fi">rakenteistettu kuvailu</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="fi">Merkitsemistapa, jossa merkkijono on ihmissilmin luettava merkkijonon merkintäjärjestelmään perustuva entiteetin kokonainen tai osittainen kuvailu tai kontrolloitu entiteetin ominaisuutta kuvaava termi.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="fi">Merkitsemistapa sisältää hakutiedon tai sanaston merkintäjärjestelmän kontrolloidun termin.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">descripció estructurada</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="ca">descripció estructurada</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="ca">Cadena que és una descripció completa o parcial d'una entitat basada en una sintaxi o en una cadena d'esquema de codificació o un terme descriu un aspecte d'una entitat.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="ca">Inclou un punt d'accés o un terme controlat obtingut d'un esquema de codificació d'un vocabulari.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">δομημένη περιγραφή</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="el">δομημένη περιγραφή</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="el">Μια μέθοδος καταγραφής που είναι είτε ένας αλφαριθμητικός χαρακτήρας σε μορφή αναγνώσιμη από άνθρωπο, ο οποίος είναι μια πλήρης ή μερική περιγραφή μιας οντότητας που βασίζεται σε ένα αλφαριθμητικό σχήμα κωδικοποίησης είτε ένας ελεγχόμενος όρος που περιγράφει μια οντότητα. </rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="el">Περιλαμβάνει ένα σημείο πρόσβασης ή έναν ελεγχόμενο όρο ο οποίος αντλείται από ένα σχήμα κωδικοποίησης [του] λεξιλογίου. </skos:scopeNote>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">strukturert beskrivelse</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="no">strukturert beskrivelse</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="no">En tekststreng basert på en syntaks eller et kodeskjema og som er en helt eller delvis menneskelig lesbar beskrivelse av en entitet eller en kontrollert term som beskriver et aspekt ved en entitet.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="no">Inkluderer en søkeinngang eller en kontrollert term hentet fra et kodeskjema for vokabular.</skos:scopeNote>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">Strukturierte Beschreibung</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="de">Strukturierte Beschreibung</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="de">Eine Erfassungsmethode in Form einer menschenlesbaren Zeichenkette, bei der es sich um eine vollständige oder teilweise Beschreibung einer Entität, die auf einem String Encoding Scheme basiert, oder um eine normierte Bezeichnung, die eine Eigenschaft einer Entität beschreibt, handelt.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="de">Eine Erfassungsmethode in Form einer menschenlesbaren Zeichenkette, bei der es sich um eine vollständige oder teilweise Beschreibung einer Entität, die auf einem String Encoding Scheme basiert, oder um eine normierte Bezeichnung, die eine Eigenschaft einer Entität beschreibt, handelt.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="de">Darunter fallen auch Sucheinstiege oder normierte Bezeichnungen, die einem Vocabulary Encoding Scheme entnommen sind.</skos:scopeNote>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="fr">Méthode d’enregistrement qui consiste soit en une chaîne lisible par l’humain et constituée d’une description complète ou partielle d’une entité basée sur un schéma d’encodage de chaînes, soit en un terme contrôlé décrivant un aspect d’une entité.</skos:definition>
        <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">strukturált leírás</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="hu">strukturált leírás</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="hu">A rögzítés egy módja, ami egy olyan emberi szemmel olvasható karakterlánc, amely egy entitásnak egy szintaxison vagy karakterlánc-kódolási sémán alapuló teljes vagy részleges leírása, vagy egy kontrollált kifejezés egy entitás egy aspektusának leírására.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="hu">A rögzítés egy módja, ami egy olyan emberi szemmel olvasható karakterlánc, amely egy entitásnak egy szintaxison vagy karakterlánc-kódolási sémán alapuló teljes vagy részleges leírása, vagy egy kontrollált kifejezés egy entitás egy aspektusának leírására.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="hu">Idetartoznak a hozzáférési pontok vagy egy szótár kódolási sémájából származó kontrollált kifejezések.</skos:scopeNote>
        <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">descrizione strutturata</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="it">descrizione strutturata</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="it">Metodo di registrazione che usa una stringa che è una descrizione, completa o parziale e in una forma leggibile dall'uomo, di una entità basata su una sintassi o su uno schema di codifica di stringhe o su un termine controllato che descrive un aspetto di un'entità.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="it">Stringa che è una descrizione completa o parziale di una entità basata su una sintassi o su uno schema di codifica di una stringa o un termine controllato che descrive un aspetto di un'entità.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="it">Include punti d'accesso o termini controllati tratti da un vocabolario di uno schema di codifica.</skos:scopeNote>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="et">struktureeritud kirjeldus</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="et">struktureeritud kirjeldus</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="et">Märkimisviis on inimloetav string, mis on stringilisel märkimissüsteemil põhinev olemi täielik või osaline kirjeldus või olemi mingit aspekti kirjeldav kontrollitav termin.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="et">Märkimisviis on inimloetav string, mis on stringilisel märkimissüsteemil põhinev olemi täielik või osaline kirjeldus või olemi mingit aspekti kirjeldav kontrollitav termin.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="et">Hõlmab leksikaalsest märkimissüsteemist võetud otsielementi ja kontrollitavat terminit.</skos:scopeNote>
    </skos:Concept>
<!-- Concept: unstructured description  -->
    <skos:Concept rdf:about="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDARecordingMethods/1001" xml:lang="en">
      <skos:inScheme rdf:resource="http://rdaregistry.info/termList/RDARecordingMethods"/>
      <reg:status rdf:resource="http://metadataregistry.org/uri/RegStatus/1001"/>
      
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">unstructured description</skos:prefLabel>
      <skos:notation>1001</skos:notation>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="en">unstructured description</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="en">A recording method that is a human-readable string that is an uncontrolled full or partial description of an entity or an uncontrolled term describing an aspect of an entity.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="en">Includes a note, a transcription, a name or title as it appears in a source of information, and an uncontrolled term.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">description non structurée</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="fr">description non structurée</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="fr">Méthode d’enregistrement qui consiste en une chaîne lisible par l’humain et constituée d’une description complète ou partielle non contrôlée d’une entité ou d’un terme non contrôlé décrivant un aspect d’une entité.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="fr">Comprend une note, une transcription, un nom ou un titre tel qu’il figure sur une source d’information et un terme non contrôlé.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">ustruktureret beskrivelse</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="da">ustruktrureret beskrivelse</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="da">Streng, der er en ukontrolleret hel eller delvis beskrivelse af en entitet eller et ukontrolleret udtryk, der beskriver et aspekt af en entitet.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="da">Omfatter en note, en transskription, et navn eller en titel som den optræder i en informationskilde, og en ukontrolleret term.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">rakenteistamaton kuvailu</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="fi">rakenteistamaton kuvailu</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="fi">Merkitsemistapa, jossa merkkijono on kontrolloimaton ihmissilmin luettava kokonainen tai osittainen entiteetin kuvailu tai kontrolloimaton entiteetin ominaisuutta kuvaava termi.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="fi">Merkitsemistapa sisältää huomautuksen, transkriboinnin tai tiedonlähteessä esiintyvässä muodossa olevan nimen tai nimekkeen sekä kontrolloimattoman termin.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">descripció no estructurada</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="ca">descripció no estructurada</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="ca">Cadena que és una descripció no controlada completa o parcial d'una entitat o un terme no controlat que descriu un aspecte d'una entitat.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="ca">Inclou una nota, una transcripció, un nom o un títol tal com figura a la font d'informació, i un terme no controlat.</skos:scopeNote>
      <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">μη δομημένη περιγραφή</skos:prefLabel>
      <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="el">μη δομημένη περιγραφή</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
      
      <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="el">Μια μέθοδος καταγραφής που είναι ένας αλφαριθμητικός χαρακτήρας σε μορφή αναγνώσιμη από άνθρωπο, ο οποίος είναι μια μη ελεγχόμενη πλήρης ή μερική περιγραφή μιας οντότητας ή ένας μη ελεγχόμενος όρος που περιγράφει μια πτυχή μιας οντότητας. </rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
      <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="el">Περιλαμβάνει μια σημείωση, μια μεταγραφή, ένα όνομα ή τίτλο όπως εμφανίζεται στην πηγή πληροφοριών και έναν μη ελεγχόμενο όρο. </skos:scopeNote>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">ustrukturert beskrivelse</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="no">ustrukturert beskrivelse</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="no">En ukontrollert tekststreng som er en menneskelig lesbar hel eller delvis beskrivelse av en entitet, eller en ukontrollert term som beskriver et aspekt ved en entitet.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="no">Inkluderer en note, en transkripsjon, et navn eller en tittel slik det forekommer i en informasjonskilde, og en ukontrollert term.</skos:scopeNote>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">Unstrukturierte Beschreibung</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="de">Unstrukturierte Beschreibung</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="de">Eine Erfassungsmethode in Form einer menschenlesbaren Zeichenkette, bei der es sich um eine nicht-normierte vollständige oder teilweise Beschreibung einer Entität oder um eine nicht-normierte Bezeichnung handelt, die eine Eigenschaft einer Entität beschreibt.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="de">Eine Erfassungsmethode in Form einer menschenlesbaren Zeichenkette, bei der es sich um eine nicht-normierte vollständige oder teilweise Beschreibung einer Entität oder um eine nicht-normierte Bezeichnung handelt, die eine Eigenschaft einer Entität beschreibt.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="de">Darunter fallen auch Anmerkungen, Transkriptionen, Namen oder Titel, wie sie in der Informationsquelle erscheinen, und nicht-normierte Bezeichnungen.</skos:scopeNote>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="fr">Méthode d’enregistrement qui consiste en une chaîne lisible par l’humain et constituée d’une description complète ou partielle non contrôlée d’une entité ou d’un terme non contrôlé décrivant un aspect d’une entité.</skos:definition>
        <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">strukturálatlan leírás</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="hu">strukturálatlan leírás</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="hu">A rögzítés egy módja, ami egy olyan emberi szemmel olvasható karakterlánc, amely egy entitás nem-kontrollált, teljes vagy részleges leírása, vagy egy nem-kontrollált kifejezés egy entitás egy aspektusának leírására.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="hu">A rögzítés egy módja, ami egy olyan emberi szemmel olvasható karakterlánc, amely egy entitás nem-kontrollált, teljes vagy részleges leírása, vagy egy nem-kontrollált kifejezés egy entitás egy aspektusának leírására.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="hu">Idetartoznak a megjegyzések, a tükrözött információk, a név és a cím, ahogy az adatforráson megjelenik, és a nem-kontrollált kifejezések.</skos:scopeNote>
        <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">descrizione non strutturata</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="it">descrizione non strutturata</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="it">Metodo di registrazione che usa una stringa che è una descrizione non controllata, completa o parziale e in una forma leggibile dall'uomo, di un'entità, o un termine non controllato che descrive un aspetto di un'entità.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="it">Stringa che è una descrizione non controllata completa o parziale di una entità, o un termine non controllato che descrive un aspetto di un'entità.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="it">Comprende note, trascrizioni, nomi o titoli come appaiono in una fonte di informazione e termini non controllati.</skos:scopeNote>
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="et">struktureerimata kirjeldus</skos:prefLabel>
        <rdakit:toolkitLabel xml:lang="et">struktureerimata kirjeldus</rdakit:toolkitLabel>
        <skos:definition xml:lang="et">Märkimisviis on inimloetav string, mis on olemi mittekontrollitav täielik või osaline kirjeldus või olemi mingit aspekti kirjeldav mittekontrollitav termin.</skos:definition>
        <rdakit:toolkitDefinition xml:lang="et">Märkimisviis on inimloetav string, mis on olemi mittekontrollitav täielik või osaline kirjeldus või olemi mingit aspekti kirjeldav mittekontrollitav termin.</rdakit:toolkitDefinition>
        <skos:scopeNote xml:lang="et">Hõlmab märkust, transkriptsiooni, nime või pealkirja andmeallikas esineval kujul ja mittekontrollitavat terminit.</skos:scopeNote>
    </skos:Concept>

<!-- Status properties used in this document  -->
    <skos:Concept rdf:about="http://metadataregistry.org/uri/RegStatus/1001">
        <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Published</skos:prefLabel>
    </skos:Concept>

</rdf:RDF>